Hey בוקר טוב *boker tov*, גוט חודש *gut chodesh*, it’s ראש חודש
סיון *Rosh Chodesh Sivan*,
and 45th day of the עומר *Omer*, today is דף ל"ב *daf
lamed bet*. Let’s just pick up from we already read the beginning
of the משנה mishna *Mishnah* on the bottom of ל"א ע"ב *lamed
aleph amud bet*, but we might as well start from there. Beginning
of a new פרק *perek*. כל הפסולים ששחטו she-shachtu שחיטתן כשרה *kol
hapsulim sheshachtu shechitatan kesherah*. Any of the invalid people, a פסול pasul
*pasul* who’s not a כהן kohen *Kohen*, an אונן *onen*, or a
טמא tamei, *tameh*, etc., who does the act of slaughtering, it’s valid
because it doesn’t require כהן kohen *Kohen*, so there really are no
requirements in terms of the personal status of the
person. ששחיטה כשרה בזרים ובנשים ובעבדים ובטמאים *sheshchita keshera bezarim uvenashim uvavadim
uvitmeim*, even בקדשי קדשים *bekodshei kodashim*, even the holiest of sacrifices, meaning
everything basically that’s not a שלמים *shlamim* that has to be slaughtered
like on the north of the מזבח *mizbeach*, etc. ובלבד שלא יהיו
טמאים נוגעים בבשר *uvilvad shelo yiheyu tameim nogim babasar*. The one requirement
is that if you're טמא tamei, *tameh*, be careful not to touch
the meat and to make the meat impure. לפיכך *lefichach*, and because
all of the invalid people can do a שחיטה shchita *shechita*, if
they do a שחיטה shchita *shechita* and have a bad thought, have
a thought about פיגול *piggul* thought, הם פוסלים במחשבה *heim poslim bemachshava*.
Because their act is legitimate, their thought is also meaningful. So therefore,
the owner's thought is irrelevant, that’s technically the point. The only relevant
thought is the thought of the person doing the עבודה avoda, *avoda*.
But שחיטה shchita. *shechita*, because it is one of the four basic
acts that make the קרבן korban כשר kosher *korban kasher*, and that
because so whoever is doing the שחיטה shchita. *shechita*, whether they’re כהן
kohen *Kohen* or non-כהן kohen *Kohen*, it’s not about being a
כהן kohen *Kohen* or not being an owner, whatever. It’s not about
the owner. It’s not specifically about the כהן kohen *Kohen*, it’s about
the person doing the עבודה avoda, *avoda*. So out of three of
those four acts, that means it’s going to be the כהן kohen,
*Kohen* doing the עבודה *avoda*, not any other כהן kohen. *Kohen*. By
the act of שחיטה shchita. *shechita*, it’s whoever’s doing the שחיטה shchita
*shechita*. Okay, and we mentioned the other day, just to mention quickly,
that תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* first of all points out the idea that
women can שחט shacht *shacht*, even by קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*, even לכתחילה
le-chatchila. *lechatchila*, against this חומרא *chumra* that appears in this book called
הלכות ארץ ישראל *Hilchot Eretz Yisrael*, and so on. And number two,
a טמא tamei *tameh* person, where does the טמא tamei *tameh* person
stand? If you have to stand outside depending on how what’s the
nature of your טומאה tuma, *tumah*, you might have to stand outside
the עזרת נשים ezrat nashim. *Ezrat Nashim*. How do you get a
knife that long? Meaning if you’re able to stand right by the
line between עזרת נשים ezrat nashim, *Ezrat Nashim* and עזרת ישראל *Ezrat
Yisrael*, okay, that you could do. You have the animals right over
the line and you’re on the other side of the line, because
you might remember we learned this in the first פרק *perek*, that
the actual שחיטה shchita *shechita* because it’s כשר kosher *kasher* with a
non-כהן kohen. *Kohen*, the person doing the שחיטה shchita *shechita* doesn’t even
have to stand in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beit Hamikdash*. A
טמא tamei *tameh* person isn’t allowed in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
*Beit Hamikdash* proper. So the way you would do it is he
would stand or she would stand on this side of the line
and the בהמה *behema* would be on the other side of the
line. But if your טומאה tumah *tumah* is something that requires you
to be outside of the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim, *Ezrat Nashim*, technically
it’s a little difficult to imagine how that would get done. Anyway,
so now the משנה mishna *Mishnah* continues.
So you have a כשר kosher שחיטה shchita, *kasher shechita* despite all
that. Right.
וכולן שקיבלו את הדם *vechulan shekiblu et hadam*. Now, all of these
פסול pasul *passul* people, so for שחיטה shchita *shechita* their דעת *daat*
is meaningful, their intent is meaningful. However, for the other acts, because
the act is invalid done by them, so they also don’t make
פיגול *piggul*. Okay, וכולן שקיבלו את הדם חוץ לזמנו וחוץ למקומו *vechulan
shekiblu et hadam chutz lizmano vechutz limkomo*. If any of these invalid
people caught the blood with the thought about wrong time or wrong
place, now, so they don’t invalidate it, they don’t make it פיגול
*piggul*, and because they don’t invalidate it or make it פיגול *piggul*,
then okay, but it’s still a פסול pasul *passul* person doing it.
The קרבן korban *korban* isn’t going to be כשר kosher *kasher*. Ah,
but if there’s more blood, get somebody כשר kasher *kasher* to do
it with the remaining of remainder of the blood. אם יש דם
הנפש *im yesh dam hanefesh*, if the animal is still spurting out
its, you know, blood, its soul blood, יחזור הכשר ויקבל yachzor hakasher
veyekabel. *yachazor hakasher veyekabel*. Get a כשר kasher *kasher* person to catch
the remaining of the blood. If all the blood was already caught
by this פסול pasul *passul* person, so there’s nothing left to do.
Meaning, he didn’t make it פיגול *piggul* or whatever, but like there’s
no you can’t make the קרבן korban כשר kasher *korban kasher*, you
need a כשר kasher *kasher* person to catch the blood. But if
that blood is still coming out of the neck of the animal,
get a כשר kasher *kasher* person to do it. Okay,
which is telling you an important הלכה halacha *halacha*, which is that
just because a פסול pasul *passul* person does a certain stage of
the עבודה *avoda*, it does not that’s not an act that invalidates,
like it positively invalidates. It’s the absence of something that makes it
valid, but it is not like an active stigma that invalidates it.
Okay, so therefore if there’s an opportunity to do it again, you
can do it again. So some things you can't do again. If
somebody שחט *shacht* the animal incorrectly, it’s not about a פסול pasul
*passul* person as we just learned, but שחט *shacht* it incorrectly, let's
say, there's no way you can שחט *shacht* it again. Okay, but
if you caught the blood with a פסול pasul *passul* person, that
didn't actively invalidate, it just did not make it good, so if
there's more blood to catch, do it again. If you threw the
blood with a פסול pasul *passul* person, presumably we'll talk about that
in a minute, okay, that maybe is more debatable, but if it
were to be the same as catching the blood, it wouldn't invalidate,
and then if you had a more blood left over, let a
כשר kasher. *kasher* person throw the blood. Okay.
What if you had a פסול pasul *passul* כהן kohen *Kohen* walking
over the blood and then that's only part that was of the
non-כשר kasher *kasher* כהן kohen *Kohen*, then would it be good since
you don't need הולכה holacha *holacha* anyway or is it the act
of that כהן kohen? *Kohen* that ruins it?
No, well, it's neither. You'd have to do it again, I mean,
you should
do it again.
I don't wait, so then you'd be stuck. Okay, but that's actually
next line. Let's keep on reading. Okay, now, קיבל הכשר *kibel hakasher*.
Okay now קיבל הכשר ונתן לפסול a כשר kasher כהן kohen's caught
it and now he gives it to an invalid כהן kohen so
the invalid כהן kohen is going to do the transporting of it
יחזיר לכשר yachzir l'kasher give it back to the כשר kosher. person
and do a redo. Okay now if now you might remember that
this has to do with all discussion about הולכה שלא ברגל holacha
shelo beregel is that considered הולכה holacha and so on but anyway
the simple sense of the משנה mishna is like the idea of
catching the blood that the transporting did not invalidate, it did not
validate, and therefore just do it again. Okay bring it back and
do it
again. Okay קיבל בימינו
ונתן לשמאלו kibel biyemino venatan lismoalo you caught it in your right
hand and you put it into your left hand so that's an
invalid way of transporting the blood doing it with your left hand
יחזיר לימינו yachzir leyemino put it back in your right hand, did
not invalidate it but it wasn't כשר kosher. so get restore it
and do it again. Okay now קיבל בכלי kibel bikli you caught
it in the what?
בכלי קודש bikli kodesh
thank you, you you you caught it in the the sanctified vessel
ונתן לכלי חול venatan likli chol and now you pour it into
an unsanctified vessel, now obviously in an unsanctified vessel it can't be
transported. That did not again actively invalidate it יחזיר לכלי קודש yachzir
likli kodesh put it back into the holy vessel so all these
same rule, these things do not actively invalidate, they're just not כשר
kosher so do a redo. Okay נשפך מן הכלי על הרצפה nishpach
min hakli al haritzpa now remember when it hits the when it
went from the neck of the animal straight to the floor you
can't gather it off the floor you have to catch it directly
in the vessel from the neck of the animal. But if you
were caught from the neck of the animal in the vessel and
then it spilled, okay so the act of catching was correct now
it's just that on the floor that again does not invalidate it
and
ואספו va'asfo you gather it up the blood כשר it's valid. So
all these things
don't make it good but they don't invalidate it either and if
you're able to do a redo you do a redo.
So even if you have enough in the vessel you should still
try to gather it all?
Oh I suppose that's true I mean it would still be כשר
if you had some stuff left but it's still better to put
it all on the altar. Okay. נתנה גבי הכבש שלא כנגד היסוד
netana gabi hakevesh shelo keneged hayesod או כמה שלא כנגד היסוד o
kama shelo keneged hayesod comma, you put it on the ramp, you
threw the blood on the ramp not on the actual walls of
the altar itself or you threw it at the at the corners
of the altar but not at the corner where there's no base
below, no protruding base below which is not a legitimate place on
the altar to put it. Okay את הניתנין למטה למעלה ואת הניתנין
למעלה למטה et hanitnin lemata lemala ve'et hanitnin lemala lemata or stuff
that was supposed to go below the line you put it above
or below the line you put it above so you put it
in the altar or in the region of the altar but in
the wrong place. Okay ואת הניתנין בפנים בחוץ ואת הניתנין בחוץ בפנים
ve'et hanitnin bifnim bachutz ve'et hanitnin bachutz bifnim or inner altar blood
on the outer outer altar blood on the inner in all these
cases אם יש דם הנפש יחזור הכשר ויקבל im yesh dam hanefesh
yachzor hakasher veyekabel if there's more blood do it again. Now this
is the biggest חידוש chiddush it's basically a similar example as all
the other examples these things don't invalidate do it again. Okay but
this is less clear because this actually is the final act and
the way the גמרא Gemara frames it there's a question whether like
זריקה עושה שיריים zarika ose shirayim whether once you do that final
act even if does that mean that anything left is defined now
as the remnant blood once you've done the זריקה? zarika? And therefore
because it's defined as the remnant blood it cannot be reused to
still do it if the if that was bad. So that's the
question about the status of זריקה. zarika. So there're two ways of
reading the end of this משנה mishna. and you might also remember
that there's a debate in the גמרא Gemara whether שלא במקומו כמקומו
דמי shelo bimkomo kimkomo dami whether if it's on the altar but
in the wrong place is it still considered like a valid sacrifice
just not you know maybe you can't eat the meat or whatever.
Okay so there's so this last piece there's two basic ways to
read it. One way to read it is is that on the
wrong place of the altar is not like you put it on
the altar. Okay and that's why you can you know and therefore
you know go ahead and do it again. Okay you know what
let's read רש''י. Rashi. רש''י Rashi actually says this more succinctly than
I can. יחזור הכשר ויקבל. So רש''י Rashi says the following: אי
סבירא לן i sevira lan דפסול עושה שיריים depasul ose shirayim so
presumably we're talking that you're now that's the question: is the end
of this משנה mishna. talking about an invalid person put it at
the wrong place of the altar? Are we still using the scenarios
in the beginning about an invalid person? Or are we saying anybody
even a כשר כהן kohen, put it in the wrong place of
the altar? So there's like a couple of ways of explaining the
end of this משנה. mishna So let's assume we're talking because that's
the larger context that a פסול pasul כהן kohen, put it in
the wrong place on the altar. Okay? So אי סבירא לן i
sevira lan if we're of the opinion דפסול עושה שיריים depasul ose
shirayim that a פסול pasul כהן kohen who were to put the
blood on the right place of the altar would make the remnant
blood considered remnant and it could no longer be used so that
actually would not directly invalidate but indirectly invalidate because it would mean
you're done, you can't do anything more after the blood is on
the altar. If that's true even for an invalid person okay so
then אשמעינן האי תנא דשלא במקומו לאו כמקומו דמי. ashmieinan hai tanna
deshelo bimkomo lav kimkomo dami. So if you're a normal invalid person
and you put it on the altar there's no then. That was
the end of the sacrifice. If you put it in the right
place of the altar and you can't go back and get more
blood. Okay, and the reason this is good is because it was
the wrong place of the altar. So that's like you did nothing
and that allows you to get more blood. You get it? So
if you're an invalid person and you do it in the right
place, that's worse than הולכה or קבלה kabala or whatever that ends.
You put it's on the right place in the altar, nothing more
can be done. Okay, and then you're stuck. It's invalid. The reason
this is valid is because it's the wrong place of the altar
so it's like you didn't do anything yet so get more blood.
That's one way of reading it. Okay, ואי סבירא לן ve-ee sevira
lan Rashi says דשלא במקומו כמקומו דמי deshelo bimkomo kimkomo dami but
if you consider this to be close enough and it's basically like
it's the right place on the altar so then why can you
get more blood? So the only thing that you can infer from
this is that a פסול pasul is אינו עושה שיריים. eino ose
shirayim. Okay, הוי ליה זריקה גמורה באדם פסול אשמעינן דאין פסול עושה
שיריים. hava lei zrika gemura be-adam pasul ashmeinan de-ein pasul ose shirayim.
Okay, so that's by the way assuming that we're talking about a
פסול pasul person doing it at the end of this משנה. mishna,
There's a third read that we're not even talking about another that
we're not even talking about a פסול pasul person but the basic
point is this משנה mishna is telling you in this case of
שלא במקומו shelo bimkomo you can still go ahead and get more
blood. And there's one of two reasons Rashi says, I mean there's
multiple ways you could read this משנה, Mishna but the simply one
of two reasons why. Either because it's in the wrong place that
means it's like nothing happened and you can get more blood but
if it's in the right place you're stuck and the blood can
no longer be used. Okay, or because it's a פסול person who
did it. And because it's a פסול person who did it that's
why it's like nothing happened and therefore even when a פסול person
does it and even when a פסול person puts it on the
altar, nothing happened really, no, nothing happened let's keep on going and
therefore you can go ahead and get more blood. Okay, even if
it's in the right place. Even according to that read even in
the right place. Okay, so there's two possibilities why it's like nothing
happened here. Is it because a פסול person did it and therefore
even in the right place it's just doesn't matter פסול person did
it nothing happened get more blood. Or is it no it's only
because it's the wrong place it's like nothing happened. Right, in which
case you can say even if a כשר person did it it's
the wrong place so you can still go back and redo it.
Right, that would be the difference. Which is the way I was
thinking of it actually. Right, meaning there are two scenarios to ask.
פסול person doing it in the right
place, okay, that you could say because it's פסול nothing happened do
it again or because you could say because it's the right place
you can't do it again or כשר person does it in the
wrong place. Okay, there you could say because it's the wrong place
that presumably is obvious. Well not well no if שלא במקומו לאו
כמקומו דמי shelo bimkomo lav kimkomo dami if it's really considered the
wrong place, okay, then yes go ahead and do it again. All
right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: שחטו shchato
so שחטו. shchato. דיעבד אין לכתחילה לא. de-eved in le-chatchila lo. So
the משנה Mishna says if they slaughtered ששחטו excuse me if they
slaughtered it's כשר. That suggests that all these פסול people should not
שחט לכתחילה. l'chatchila, ורמינהי u-raminihi but I'll ask you on these,
I'll ask you on this:
ושחט. ve-shacht. It says you know when it speaks about the שחיטה
shchita, ושחט את בן הבקר. ve-shacht et ben habakar. שחיטה בזר כשרה.
shchita be-zar keshera. So since it doesn't say ושחט הכהן ve-shacht hakohen
it just speaks about the owner bringing it and says and then
he shall slaughter and it hasn't introduced yet the כהן, that's how
the גמרא Gemara infers that שחיטה Shechita, can be done by a
non-כהן. It only starts mentioning the כהנים kohanim when it speaks about
catching the blood. So שהשחיטה כשרה בזר she-hashchita keshera be-zar it's כשר
שהשחיטה בזר כשרה she-hashchita be-zar keshera שהשחיטה כשרה בזרים ובנשים she-hashchita keshera
be-zarim u-venashim non-כהנים, kohanim, women, ועבדים ve-avadim slaves, וטמאים u-tmeiyim and even
ואפילו בקדשי קדשים. va-afilu be-kadshei kodashim. This is all continuing this מדרש
הלכה. midrash halacha. או אינו אלא בכהנים o eino ela be-kohanim maybe
it's only maybe no ושחט ve-shacht means a כהן.
אמרת וכי מאין באת. amarta ve-chi me-ayin bata. What would motivate you
to say כהן since the verse doesn't even say כהן by the
שחיטה. Shechita What would sort of be your orientation, where are you
coming from that you would assume כהן? So וכי מאין באת ve-chi
me-ayin bata מכלל שנאמר michlal shene-emar because the verse says ואתה ובניך
אתך תשמרו את כהונתכם לכל דבר המזבח. ve-ata uvaneycha itcha tishmeru et
kehunatchem lechol dvar hamizbeach. You should protect the כהונה kehuna for all
matters relating to the altar. So all matters relating to the altar
might mean anything that has to do with turning this into the
stuff that's going to go on the altar is a כהן's domain.
So therefore even though the verse doesn't say the כהן שחטס shachts
since it says the כהן has to protect all matters related to
the altar it would be reasonable to think this would be included.
Okay, יכול אף בשחיטה yachol af be-shchita so I might think that
includes
שחיטה. Shechita. תלמוד לומר talmud lomar
ושחט את בן הבקר לפני ה' והקריבו בני אהרן הכהנים את הדם.
ve-shacht et ben habakar lifnei Hashem ve-hikrivu bnei Aharon hakohanim et hadam.
So no if you read the פסוק pasuk closely it says the
owner brings it and slaughters it before God and then it says
and the כהנים kohanim bring the blood close. So the תורה Torah
actually is very careful to only mention כהנים kohanim after it mentions
the blood. כהנים kohanim only once it becomes the blood issue not
at the act of שחיטה. Shechita Very good close read of the
פסוק. pasuk. מקבלה ואילך מצות כהונה mi-kabala va-eilach mitzvat kehuna from catching
the blood onward that's when it's about the כהנים. kohanim. לימד על
השחיטה שכשרה בכל אדם. limed al hashchita she-keshera be-chol adam. Okay שחיטה
Shechita is כשר with any person. So anyway that's the מדרש הלכה
midrash halacha so that's nice it tells us where we get it
from very nice close read of the verse. But the language of
that תוספתא, Tosefta, of that, of that מדרש הלכה, Midrash Halacha, of
that ברייתא, Braita, makes it clear that we have no compunction with
anybody doing the שחיטה לכתחילה. shchita l'chatchila. שחיטה שבזר ובנשים Shchita she'b'zar
u'v'nashim like it's absolutely no problem, right? So if that's true, why
was our משנה mishna, framed in a בדיעבד b'diavad way? If they
שחטו, shechted, it's כשר. So the גמרא Gemara says: הוא הדין, Hu
hadin, it's really the same case, דאפילו לכתחילה נמי, d'afilu l'chatchila nami,
that actually you're right, all these people could do it לכתחילה, l'chatchila.
no problem, no hesitation whatsoever. Except when משום דקבעי למתני טמאים, mishum
d'ka'baei l'misni t'me'im, since one of the people in this משנה is
a טמא, tamei, and again תוספות Tosafos points out that's the only
person we have an issue with, not with women, they could even
be לכתחילה. l'chatchila Because it's going to mention טמא, tamei דלכתחילה לא,
d'l'chatchila lo, טמאים לכתחילה t'me'im l'chatchila should not do it. Why not?
גזרה שמא יגעו בבשר. Gezeira shema yigu b'vasar. Because we're afraid they
might come to touch the meat. And because of the concern that
they might come to touch the meat, right, therefore that we say
a טמא tamei, person shouldn't do it. As far as the act
of שחיטה Shechita is concerned, it's a total 100% כשר. Because of
some, you know, related issues that you know, that might happen accidentally,
there we want to say a טמא tamei, person לכתחילה l'chatchila, shouldn't
do it, but as far as the שחיטה Shechita is concerned, 100%.
And with everybody else, 100%. תוספות Tosafos points out that it's interesting
that we're not concerned that the טמא tamei person might step over
the line and enter into the into the עזרה. Azara. תוספות Tosafos
says, you know, if you're טמא, tamei, you're sort of on your
guard, you're more aware, you know, therefore you will be careful about
where that line is. It's actually more of a danger somebody isn't
טמא tamei, and shouldn't be going in or whatever, you know, that's
in general an issue. Like it's more of a problem eating meat
at the same table with somebody eating milk because it's all כשר
stuff, than it is eating something at the same table with somebody
eating חזיר. chazir. Like if something is clearly off-limits, you know, you're
more on your guard. So תוספות Tosafos says if you know you're
טמא, Tamei we're not afraid you'll step over the line. The only
real concern is that you'll touch the meat. Yeah, the תוספות Tosafot
points out, not worried that he's going to start to do the
other stuff, you know. Right, right, that's a good point. Okay, so
it says like this, okay, so that's why לכתחילה לא. l'chatchila lo.
משום דבעי למתני טמאים דלכתחילה לא גזרה שמא יגעו בבשר תנא ששחטו.
Mishum d'ba'ei l'misni t'me'im d'l'chatchila lo gezeira shema yigu b'vasar tana she'shachtu.
That's why we say שחטו בדיעבד. shachtu b'diavad. So the גמרא Gemara
says: One minute, וטמא דיעבד שפיר דמי v'tamei d'iavad shapir dami? So
now that we've gotten through saying that in principle everybody's לכתחילה, even
a טמא, tamei, as far as the act of שחיטה, Shechita? it's
only this Rabbinic safeguard. Now we're going to question the inclusion of
טמא tamei in that list. Because we're going to see an opinion
that the שוחט, shochet, not only does the animal have to be
in the עזרה, Azara, the שוחט shochet has to be in the
עזרה. Azara. So that a שוחט shochet should be a problem, not
again because somehow there's an הלכה halacha that the שוחט shochet has
to be טהור, tahor, but if you assume the שוחט shochet has
to be situated in the עזרה, Azara, then there's no way for
the שוחט shochet to be in the עזרה Azara because if he's
טמא, tamei okay. So רמי ניהו, rami nihu, I'll ask you on
this: וסמך ושחט. v'samach v'shachat. You should put your hand on the
animal, וסמך את ידו, v'samach et yado, whatever, and then it says
and you shall slaughter it. So those two verbs are juxtaposed. מה
סמיכה בטהורים אף שחיטה בטהורים. Ma smicha b'tehorim, af shchita b'tehorim. This
ברייתא Braita claims the same way it's obvious the סמיכה smicha you
have to be טהור. tahor. Now why that's true, the גמרא's Gemara
going to ask, because even if you're טמא, tamei, if the animal's
alive, you don't impurify it. So the גמרא Gemara says, oh, but
obviously סמיכה smicha you have to be טהור, tahor, שחיטה Shechita, you
have to be טהור. tahor. מדרבנן Mi'derabbanan? So, fine, it's only Rabbinic.
It's not biblical. So okay, now the גמרא Gemara says: One minute,
okay, fine, but what is this ברייתא Braita talking about anyway? מאי
שנא סמיכה דכתיב לפני ה׳ Mai shna smicha d'chtiv lifnei Hashem? Okay,
so according to your read that it's only Rabbinic, but why are
we assuming that סמיכה smicha sounds like that really you have to
be טהור? tahor? Why do you have to be a טהור? tahor?
'Cause it says by the סמיכה, smicha, it says you should put
your hands and it says לפני ה׳, lifnei Hashem, you should do
it in the presence of God. So in the presence of God
means that you, the סומך, someich, the person putting the hands, has
to be in the presence of God, has to be in the
עזרה. Azara. Okay, so if that's what we're saying that סמיכה smicha
you have to be טהור, tahor, and it says ושחט את בן
הבקר לפני ה׳, v'shachat et ben ha'bakar lifnei Hashem, not just... Right,
well that's the next line of the גמרא, Gemara, okay. Because it
says, but the line right before that says וסמך, v'samach, right? Does
it say וסמך v'samach there? It says וסמך v'samach I think. וסמך
ידו על ראש העולה ונרצה לו ושחט את בן הבקר לפני ה׳.
V'samach yado al rosh ha'ola v'nirtza lo, v'shachat et ben ha'bakar lifnei
Hashem. So actually לפני ה׳ lifnei Hashem is more juxtaposed to ושחט.
v'shachat. Right, okay, so fine, you get it by סמך samach only
'cause סמך samach is way earlier. So that's what the גמרא's Gemara
going to say: שחיטה נמי אכתיב לפני ה׳. Shchita nami ach'tiv lifnei
Hashem. You have to be before God. So make up your mind,
if the idea is you have to be standing in the עזרה,
Azara, and if that's true about the סומך, someich, it certainly is,
as Michael points out, certainly true about the שוחט. shochet. So how
could you say that one is דאורייתא d'oreisa and one is דרבנן?
d'rabbanan? Right, if we're taking this ברייתא Braita seriously, this ברייתא Braita
at least would claim that both of them have to be standing
in the עזרה. Azara. So the גמרא Gemara says: אפשר דעביד סכינא
ארוכה ושחיט. Efshar d'avid sakina arucha v'shachit. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says no, לפני ה׳ lifnei Hashem does not refer to you the
person. It refers to the animal. So therefore if it's just about
the animal being in the עזרה, Azara, you don't have to be,
you could have a long knife, stand over the line, and have
the animal on the other side of the line. So the גמרא
Gemara says: Okay, if it's about the animal, then that's true about
שחיטה, Shechita? it should be true about סמיכה. smicha. סמיכה נמי אפשר
דמלא ידיה וסמך. Smicha nami efshar d'malei yado v'samach. The animal could
be... The animal could be standing over the line and you just
put your hands on the head of the animal. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says, no, קסבר ביאה במקצת שמה ביאה. Kasavar bi'ah b'miktzas
shma bi'ah. No, this and this is what's going to be a
major focus for our discussion in a few minutes, this תנא Tanna
is of the opinion that when a טמא tamei? person is not
allowed to enter in to the עזרה, Azara, that even means a
tiny piece of their body is not allowed to enter in. We'll
get to that. Okay. Is not allowed to enter in. Okay. So
somebody, I remember way back when I went first time I think
I was in Israel when I was in ישיבה Yeshiva or whatever,
some people had this חומרה, chumra, you know, this was a time
when like, because ישיבה Yeshiva guys aren't supposed to be watching TV
or reading novels, so what they do with their spare time is
they think up good חומרות. chumros. So anyway, so this was a
חומרה chumra about you're not allowed to put a note into the
crack of the wall of the whatever. Why? Because it's Kotel. Because
if you're טמא, tamei, okay, and if you say that the הר
הבית Har HaBayis begins not on the inside of the wall, but
in the thickness of the wall begins הר הבית, Har HaBayis, then
when you put your finger in, that's a ביאה במקצת bi'ah b'miktzas
of your finger into the zone of הר הבית, Har HaBayis, and
if you're a טמא tamei, person who's not allowed on הר הבית,
Har HaBayis, that's a ביאה במקצת. bi'ah b'miktzas. Okay. So anyway, this
is the question about ביאה במקצת שמה ביאה bi'ah b'miktzas shma bi'ah
or לא שמה ביאה. lo shma bi'ah. So, the way it's reading
it now is, you the person don't have to be לפני ה',
Lifnei Hashem, the animal does. You're on the other side of the
line. When it comes to שחיטה, Shechita, I can do it without
my hand crossing the line, just the knife crosses the line and
cuts the neck of the animal. When it comes to סמיכה, Smicha,
presumably I can't turn the head of the animal to be over
the line, the whole animal has to be on that צד tzad
of the line, so I have to bring my hands over, and
that would be a problem. So read this way, we are saying
that סמיכה Smicha you have to be טהור tahor because you have
to get your hands in, whereas שחיטה Shechita only דרבנן-ly derabbanan you
have to be טהור tahor because of a concern of טומאה, tumah,
you might touch it, but technically you do not have to be
טהור tahor to do the שחיטה. Shechita Okay. That's one way. But
that person that holds it's not a problem, not considered ביאה במקצת?
bi'ah b'miktzas? We're going to get, we haven't seen that person. We're
going to see it in a minute. רב חסדא מתני איפכא. Rav
Chisda masni ipcha. רב חסדא Rav Chisda taught the reverse. וסמך ושחט.
V'samach v'shachat. מה שחיטה בטהורים, Mah shechita b'tahorim, the same way שחיטה
Shechita? you have to be טהור, tahor, this one assumes שחיטה Shechita
you have to be טהור, tahor, and then uses it to apply
it to סמיכה. Smicha. אף סמיכה בטהורים. Af smicha b'tahorim. So according
to this read, this read seems to be one saying, no, there
actually is a real opinion that for שחיטה Shechita you have to
be טהור. tahor. Now let's figure out why. We have yet to
come up with a good reason why. מאי שנא שחיטה דכתיב לפני
ה'? Mai shna shechita d'chsiv lifnei Hashem? So, by שחיטה shchita it
says לפני ה' Lifnei Hashem even more explicitly, and presumably that means
that you have to be, again, to read that as the reason
why, it would mean not only the animal has to be in
the עזרה, Azara, you have to be in the עזרה. Azara. So
סמיכה נמי כתיב לפני ה'? Smicha nami ksiv lifnei Hashem? So by
סמיכה Smicha also that occurred earlier in the פסוק. posuk. Why do
you have to link it to שחיטה? shchita? If you're reading לפני
ה' Lifnei Hashem means you have to be standing there when you
do the שחיטה, read it also the same way you have to
be standing in the עזרה Azara when you do the סמיכה. Smicha.
So why is it because it's linked to שחיטה? It's because both
of them it says לפני ה'. Lifnei Hashem. If that's how you
want to read לפני ה'. Lifnei Hashem. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, אפשר דמלי ידיה וסמיך. efshar d'mali yadei v'samich. No, okay, it's
not that וסמך v'samach means or ושחט v'shachat means that's where you
have to be standing. It just... so fine, the animal has to
be in the עזרה, Azara, you can be on the other side.
So סמיכה, Smicha, if it weren't linked to שחיטה, in principle there
would be no problem with סמיכה. Smicha. You just stick your hands
in. And this would assume that ביאה במקצת לא שמה ביאה, bi'ah
b'miktzas lo shma bi'ah, that sticking your hands in is not a
problem. Okay. So this one assumes the other one assumed סמיכה Smicha
fundamentally is a problem, if you're טמא tamei you're not allowed to
stick your hands in. שחיטה is a דרבנן derabbanan issue. This one
says no. We're going to say in a minute why שחיטה is
a more serious issue, but סמיכה Smicha in principle is not really
a problem because you're allowed to stick your hands in, that's only
a partial entering. So the גמרא Gemara says שחיטה נמי אפשר דעביד
סכין ארוכה ושחט. shechita nami efshar d'avid sakin aruka v'shachat. Okay, then
why if only the animal has to be in the עזרה, Azara,
why what's the problem with שחיטה? So the גמרא Gemara says הא
רבני שמעון התימני היא. ha rabanai Shimon HaTeimani hi. This is שמעון
התימני. Shimon HaTeimani. There actually is an opinion that says that as
opposed to סמיכה Smicha where we all agree you can be standing
outside and the only question is are you allowed to stick your
hands in or not, by שחיטה there actually is an opinion, against
everything we've been saying now, there actually is an opinion that by
שחיטה you have to be standing in the עזרה Azara itself, which
sort of is intuitive because if it's an עבודה, you would want
the guy standing in the עזרה, Azara, but of course the person
doesn't have to be a כהן, so you certainly understand the reason
why once you're not a כהן, who needs that you be standing
in the עזרה. Azara. But שמעון התימני Shimon HaTeimani says no, even
if you're not a כהן you have to stand in the עזרה.
Azara. דתניא ושחט את בן הבקר לפני ה', detanya v'shachat es ben
habakar lifnei Hashem, and here again לפני ה' Lifnei Hashem as Michael
correctly said is juxtaposed to the word ושחט. v'shachat. So the גמרא
Gemara says הנשחט לפני ה' ולא השוחט לפני ה'. hanishchat lifnei Hashem
v'lo hashochet lifnei Hashem. I think that's the גרסא. geirsa. Oh no,
בן הבקר לפני ה' ולא השוחט לפני ה'. ben habakar לפני ה'
v'lo hashochet lifnei Hashem. ושחט את בן הבקר לפני ה'. V'shachat es
ben habakar לפני ה'. The animal has to be לפני ה', Lifnei
Hashem, the animal has to be in the עזרה. Azara. בן הבקר,
Ben habakar, like those are words are... בן הבקר לפני השם ולא
השוחט לפני השם. ben habakar lifnei Hashem velo hashochet lifnei Hashem. You,
the guy who's doing the act of slaughtering, you could be on
the other side of the line. That's what we've been assuming. שמעון
התימני אומר, Shimon HaTimni omer, מניין שיהיו ידיו של שוחט לפנים מן
הנשחט? minayin sheyihyu yadav shel shochet lifnim min hanishchat? No, that's not
true. Actually, the שוחט shochet has to be more inner than the
animal that's being slaughtered, okay? שנאמר, shenemar, ושחט את בן הבקר לפני
השם, veshachat et ben habakar lifnei Hashem, שוחט את בן הבקר. shochet
et ben habakar. He actually reads the word ושחט, veshachat, the שוחט
shochet of the בן הבקר ben habakar must be לפני השם. lifnei
Hashem. שוחט את בן הבקר יהיה לפני השם. shochet et ben habakar
yihiyeh lifnei Hashem. I don't know why that means more inner than
the animal, but certainly as inner as the animal. Okay, anyway, so
שמעון התימני Shimon HaTimni just says, I don't buy this. It's not
בן הבקר לפני השם, ben habakar lifnei Hashem, it's not just the
animal has to be in the עזרה, azara, ושחט לפני השם, veshachat
lifnei Hashem, you have to be standing in the עזרה. azara. Okay,
so here's what we've got. Can you do שמיכה smicha if you're
טמא, tamei עיקר הדין, ikar hadin, right? That depends on whether you're
allowed, if whether it be במקצת שמה ביאה bemiktzat shema bia or
not. Can you do שחיטה if you're טמא? tamei Of course, the
dominant position, our משנה, whatever, everything we've quoted until now is yes,
just stay on the other side of the line, you have a
big knife, you don't have to get into the עזרה azara at
all. But שמעון התימני Shimon HaTimni says no, not for a technical
reason, there's an actual demand that the שוחט shochet be standing לפני
השם, lifnei Hashem, the שוחט shochet be in the עזרה, azara, which
is not true by the סומך somech and so on. This is
an עבודה, it needs to be in the עזרה, azara, and therefore
if you're טמא, tamei you cannot do it. Okay, yes, Mike? Isn't
there a reason to say you should be more lenient with שמיכה
smicha anyway, because you know, especially to some, אין נשים סומכות, ein
nashim somchot, or you know, you can even like, and not even
all קרבנות korbanot get a שמיכה, smicha, whereas all קרבנות have to
get some form of שחיטה? Yeah, again, I don't know if those
types of differences, those are like things when we make קל וחומר,
kal vachomer, as you have this הלכה halacha here, you have that
הלכה halachic here, so it's more weighty, not more weighty. It's better
to just learn it straight in terms of what are the requirements
we find in the פסוקים. psukim. Okay, אמר ריש לקיש, amar Reish
Lakish, אמרו לו לעולא אמר ריש לקיש, amru lo le'Ulla amar Reish
Lakish, טמא שהכניס ידו לפנים. tamei shehichnis yado lifnim. Now we're going
to step back, find those who were a fascinating debate, okay, שוחט,
shochet, you know, the consensus is you can do it if you're
טמא, tamei. you just the animal is the only thing that has
to be there, you can be on the other side. But שמיכה,
smicha, we have an open question whether you're allowed to stick your
hands in or not. Okay, and here, and here we're going to
now enter, focus on this question about entering only with part of
your body, is that considered transgressing or not? Okay, so let's take
a look. אמר עולא אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Ulla amar Reish Lakish,
טמא שהכניס ידו לפנים לוקה. tamei shehichnis yado lifnim lokei. If a
טמא tamei, person even just sticks his hand into the עזרה, azara,
he gets lashes, okay? I guess he wouldn't let a טמא tamei
do שמיכה. smicha. Well, right, so טמא tamei. wouldn't do, right, they'd
not do שמיכה, smicha, שנאמר, shenemar, בכל קודש לא תגע ואל המקדש
לא תבוא, bechol kodesh lo tiga ve'el hamikdash lo tavo, okay, and
she should not touch, עד מלאות ימי טהרה, ad milot yemei tahara,
this is by a woman who gave childbirth, she should not touch,
you know, anything that is holy, and she should not enter into
the temple until she becomes טהור. tahor. So מקיש ביאה לנגיעה. makish
bia lenegi'ah. So the act of entering in the temple is connected
to the act of touching some sacrifice. מה נגיעה במקצת, mah negi'ah
bemiktzat, when you touch a sacrifice, you don't touch it with your
whole
body, you touch it with like a finger or a hand, שמה
נגיעה, shma negi'ah, the same way that counts as touching, אף ביאה
במקצת שמה ביאה. af bia bemiktzat shma bia. So entering even with
part
of your body is entering. So now we know the basis for
the principal, for the position that ביאה במקצת שמה ביאה, bia bemiktzat
shma bia, and really it's a full transgression, you get lashes, that
is the הלכה halachah. definition of entering according to this opinion. Okay,
איתיביה רב הושעיא, Eitiveih Rav Oshaya, so רב הושעיא Rav Oshaya challenged
this, לעולא, le'Ulla, מצורע שחל שמיני שלו להיות בערב פסח. metzora shechal
shemini shelo lihyot be'erev pesach. So you've got a מצורע, metzora, it's
his eighth day, okay, and the eighth day is when he brings
his קרבן korban, and he becomes totally טהור. tahor. Now, here's the
story. Okay, if somebody is טמא on ערב פסח, erev pesach, that's
okay, you don't have to bring the קרבן korban, into the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, right? A פסח pesach anyway was brought by a
group. You have one representative of the group. You wait at home,
let's say you went to the מקוה mikvah that day, okay, and
you're going to be טהור tahor at nightfall. Fine, somebody in my
group will bring the קרבן for me to the עזרה, azara, I'll
be טהור tahor at the nightfall and I'll eat my קרבן פסח,
korban pesach, שקויעח, shkoyach, wonderful. But here's the problem. If I'm a
מצורע metzora and it's my eighth day, I have to go to
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash today because I have to finish it
up. Fine, I'll go to the בית המקדש, Beis haMikdash I'll finish
it up, either I or somebody else will bring my קרבן פסח
korban pesach and I'll eat it that night. No problem. But if
the מצורע metzora is also a בעל קרי, baal keri, okay, he
had a seminal emission the night before. So here's my problem. I
gotta go to the בית המקדש to bring my קרבן מצורע, korban
metzora, that I need to be there personally. I can't have somebody
do that for me, okay, because part of the purification process is
they put the blood on the, my thumb, or whatever. I gotta
do that personally. I gotta show up. But if this guy, he's
also a בעל קרי, baal keri, okay, he's not allowed to enter
into עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim. עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim okay, he... just
so you know, okay, this is מחנה שכינה, Machane Shechina, the עזרה,
Azara, עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim. and the whole הר הבית Har haBayit
is considered, you know, מחנה לוייה. Machane Leviyah. And then all of
ירושלים Yerushalayim is considered מחנה ישראל. Machane Yisrael. Okay. So, so you
know, so it says וישלחו מן המחנה כל צרוע וכל זב וכל
טמא לנפש. Veyishalchu min hamachane kol tzaruah vechol zav vechol tamei lanefesh.
So what the חכמים Chachamim read that is those are three different
categories and three different מחנות. machanot. So the צרוע tzaruah goes all
the way outside all three, right? בדד ישב מחוץ למחנה מושבו. Badad
yeshev michutz lamachane moshavo. וישלחו מן המחנה כל צרוע. Veyishalchu min hamachane
kol tzaruah. The זב zav goes outside, this is הר הבית. Har
haBayit. You know, the זב zav goes outside of two מחנות machanot
and included in the זב zav is anybody who has a טומאה
יוצא מגופו. tumah yotzei migufo. So that includes זבה, zavah, נדה, niddah,
בעל קרי. ba'al keri. All all those people, this is relevant if
you wanted to do a הר הבית Har haBayit tour. Anybody that
tour, tour, anybody. Now I'm getting my English and Hebrew mixed up.
Anyway, if you wanted to tour הר הבית, Har haBayit, so any
of these people you can't go onto הר הבית, Har haBayit, okay?
מצורע Metzora also. What? Well certainly a מצורע. Metzora. Okay. Okay. And
וישלחו מן המחנה כל צרוע וכל זב וכל טמא לנפש, Veyishalchu min
hamachane kol tzaruah vechol zav vechol tamei lanefesh, טמא לנפש tamei lanefesh
specifically means טמא מת. tmei meis. Okay. So somebody who has the
טומאה tumah from an external source, touched a dead carcass, touched a
dead body, and so on. Okay, that only is not allowed in
מחנה שכינה, Machane Shechina, is allowed here. This is טמא מת, tmei
meis, as the גמרא Gemara says, even מעין m'ein or including, you
know, שרץ, sheretz, נבלה, neveilah, etc. It comes from an external source.
Plus the גמרא Gemara says that even מת עצמו meis atzmo is
נכנס nichnas into מחנה לוייה Machane Leviyah because it says ויקח משה
את עצמות יוסף עמו. Vayikach Moshe et atzmot Yosef imo. So משה
Moshe is in מחנה לוייה Machane Leviyah and he's there with the
bones of יוסף, Yosef, so even the מת עצמו meis atzmo is
allowed here. Now, okay, so technically all of these people are allowed
in מחנה לוייה, Machane Leviyah, they can't go into the עזרה, Azara,
technically they could even go into עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim. But מדרבנן,
midrabonon, okay, עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim they basically said, you know, here
you have to basically מדרבנן midrabonon at least they said you have
to basically be, you know, totally טהור tahor even to get into
עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim, Okay, but מדאורייתא midoraisa really all of these
people could be in in עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim. עזרת נשים Ezrat
Nashim? is like הר הבית, Har haBayit, okay? Okay. So, let's take
a look at what we've got here. So, מצורע, Metzora, now okay,
so this guy is a מצורע. Metzora. So because he went through
the seven days of the purification process, he's allowed back in. All
right? He's not totally totally טהור tahor because he hasn't brought his
קרבן, he hasn't done the final eighth day thing, he can't go
into מחנה שכינה. Machane Shechina. But he can go all the way
up here, okay, you know, I mean the only person that's whatever
not totally טהור tahor that's allowed here is somebody who hasn't brought
his final קרבן, obviously those people are allowed, okay? מחוסר כיפורים Mechusar
kipurim is allowed here. Okay. Okay, plus מחוסר כיפורים. Mechusar kipurim. So,
a מצורע Metzora basically comes on day eight, he comes here, he's
allowed here, the only thing he's lacking that prevents him from going
into the עזרה Azara is the bringing of is the final purification
process. He comes here, he does it, there's going to be קרבן
פסח korban pesach tonight, שלום על ישראל. Shalom al Yisrael. Okay, but
he has to show up himself because of the thumbs. Now the
problem is he's also a בעל קרי. ba'al keri. As a בעל
קרי ba'al keri he's not allowed on הר הבית. Har haBayit. So
what is he going to do? Now he could go to the
מקוה. mikvah. Then he is a טבול יום tvul yom of a
בעל קרי. ba'al keri. And then, right, because only at nightfall will
he be totally טהור. tahor. So the question is, is a טבול
יום tvul yom of זב, zav, it's normally framed as זב, zav,
but you could say of בעל קרי ba'al keri like the like
the בעל קרי. ba'al keri. Is a טבול יום tvul yom of
זב כזב? zav k'zav? We had this is טבול יום tvul yom
of בעל קרי כבעל קרי? ba'al keri k'ba'al keri? So assuming even
after the מקוה mikvah he is not allowed into this zone until
nightfall, that's the question. So here's you got this guy, this poor
מצורע, metzora, he's got a problem. He's got to show up to
the בית המקדש in person in order to become טהור tahor to
be able to eat the קרבן פסח korban pesach that night. But
he's not allowed in this zone because he's a בעל קרי. ba'al
keri. So what's he going to do? How can he eat the
קרבן פסח korban pesach that night? Maybe he can't. Okay? So let's
take a look. So it says like this: מצורע שחל שמיני שלו
להיות בערב פסח, Metzora shechal shemini shelo l'hyot b'erev pesach, וראה קרי
בו ביום, v'ra'ah keri bo bayom, he became a בעל קרי ba'al
keri on that day, day eight, וטבל v'taval and he went to
the מקוה. mikvah. אמרו חכמים אף על פי שטבול יום אחר נכנס,
Amru chachamim af al pi she'tvul yom acher nichnas, even though a
normal טבול יום tvul yom is not allowed on הר הבית Har
haBayit and in the עזרת נשים, זה נכנס, zeh nichnas, we're going
to let this guy. Why? מוטב שיבוא עשה שיש בו כרת Mutav
sheyavo asei sheyesh bo kares on פסח Pesach. *Pesach* which is an
עשה asei *asei* that has כרת kares *kares*, very weighty, right, and
he wants, obviously, we want him to be able to do it,
וידחה עשה asei, שאין בו כרת *v'yidchei asei she'ein bo kares*. We'll
push away the עשה *asei* that doesn't have כרת *kares* that is
preventing him from הר הבית Har Habayit? *Har HaBayis*. Which עשה *asei*
is preventing this guy from הר הבית Har Habayit, *Har HaBayis*? Well,
the פסוק *pasuk* says, right, וישלחו מן המחנה *v'ishalchu min hamachaneh*, וישלחו
מן המחנה *v'ishalchu min hamachaneh* כל צרוע *kol tsaru'a*, right, וכל זב
zav *v'khol zav*, right, that's why we have three different camps, וכל
טמא לנפש *v'khol tamei l'nefesh*, right? Now, that is a מצות עשה
mitzvot asei *mitzvas asei*. Then it says, ולא יטמאו את מחניהם *v'lo
yitam'u es mahanehem*, מזכר ועד נקבה תשלחו *mi-zachar v'ad nekeivah tishaleichu*, whatever,
ולא יטמאו את מחניהם *v'lo yitam'u es mahanehem*, right, את מחניהם *es
mahanehem*. That is the לא תעשה *lo sa'asei*. Now, here's what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to assume. If you're a טבול יום tvul
yom *tvul yom*, you are not included in ולא יטמאו *v'lo yitam'u*,
because since you already have gone to the מקוה mikvah *mikvah* and
you're going to be totally טהור tahor *tahor* by night, your presence
is not considered to be מטמא *mitamei* the camp. Okay? You're basically
in a טהור tahor *tahor* process, there's a little residual טומאה tumah
*tumah* in you, but your presence, you know, is no longer—it's like,
you know, you got over, you know, the infectious part of your
disease, right? You're no longer contagious, you're no longer מטמא *mitamei* the
camp. So once you're a טבול יום tvul yom. *tvul yom*, even
if we consider you that you're in the category of וכל זב
zav *v'khol zav*, if you wanted to use Brisker language, בגברא *b'gavra*
you're still טמא *tamei*. You're still a זב zav *zav* or a
בעל קרי Baal Keri *ba'al keri* who's like a זב zav, *zav*
and you have to be sent away, but you don't transgress ולא
יטמאו *v'lo yitam'u* because you're not מטמא *mitamei* other things. So it
says, this guy, this טבול יום tvul yom *tvul yom* of בעל
קרי Baal Keri, *ba'al keri*, his need to keep off of הר
הבית *Har HaBayis*, that's the positive מצוה *mitzvah*. He's not included in
the negative prohibition. We will let him violate that positive מצוה *mitzvah*
and go here in order to let him do a bigger positive
מצוה *mitzvah* and eat the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach *korban pesach* this
night. Got it? Okay, so... because it's just a regular בעל קרי
Baal Keri, *ba'al keri*, he doesn't need to be there anyway, doesn't
he?
Regular בעל קרי Baal Keri, *ba'al keri*, have somebody bring it for
him. Okay. But the only—the reason this is complicated is because he
needs to
be there in person for the מצורע metzora *metzora* in order to
allow him to then get rid of the צרעת *tzara'as* status. Finish
that completely. Okay. ורבי יוחנן אמר דבר תורה Torah אפילו עשה אין
in, בה *v'Rabbi Yochanan amar d'var Torah afilu asei ein bah*. Rabbi
Yochanan says, I don't even think there's a מצות עשה mitzvot asei,
*mitzvas asei* keeping this guy off, okay? I think that once you're
a טבול יום tvul yom, *tvul yom*, you're actually like—effectively like you're
totally טהור *tahor*. Maybe again, maybe you can't enter the עזרה Azarah,
*Azarah*, whatever, but he says basically I think that a טבול יום
tvul yom
*tvul yom* is allowed on הר הבית *Har HaBayis* and in עזרת
נשים *Ezras Nashim*, okay? So I think that there's not even an
עשה *asei*, it's all rabbinic. אף טבול יום tvul yom.
אין בה *af tvul yom ein bah*. שנאמר *sh'ne'emar*... דבר תורה Torah
אפילו עשה
אין בה שנאמר *d'var Torah afilu asei ein bah sh'ne'emar*, ויעמד יהושפט
בקהל יהודה Yehudah? וירושלם בבית ה' *vaya'amod Yehoshaphat bikhal Yehudah vi-Yerushalayim b'veis
Hashem*... he stood there in the house of God... לפני החצר החדשה
*lifnei he-hatzer he-hadashah*. And we're assuming חצר החדשה *hatzer hadashah* means the
עזרת נשים *Ezras Nashim*. Okay. מאי חצר החדשה *mai hatzer hadashah*? אמר
רבי יוחנן שחידשו בה דברים *amar Rabbi Yochanan she-hiddeshu bah devarim*. ואמרו
*v'amru*, they made a whole innovation and they said, טבול יום tvul
yom אל יכנס למחנה לויה *tvul yom al yikanes l'machaneh leviyah*, a
טבול יום *tvul yom* shouldn't come onto מחנה לויה Machaneh Leviyah. *machaneh
leviyah* which means הר הבית *Har HaBayis*, okay? So therefore that's all
rabbinic, okay? דאורייתא d'oraita, *d'oraisa*, the עשה *asei* and the לא תעשה
*lo sa'asei* is only before the person has gone to the מקוה
*mikvah*. Once the person has gone to the מקוה *mikvah*, they're allowed
in this zone. Again, they might not be allowed in the עזרה
Azarah *Azarah*. That might still apply and that might even be חיוב
כרת chiyuv kares, *chiyuv kares* or whatever. But in terms of any
place that's not the מקדש *mikdash* proper, okay, that according to רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, a טבול יום *tvul yom* is allowed. So it's
only rabbinic that we say keep out of, you know, out of
like עזרת נשים *Ezras Nashim*, okay, and that will allow—that rabbinic thing
in order to allow this guy to come bring a קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach. *korban pesach*. So what's the פשט *pshat* of חצר החדשה
*hatzer hadashah*? Did they do some renovations or is it somewhere else?
What does it actually פשט *pshat*? Oh, I don't know, it assumedly
means yeah, they did some renovations, they built it up. Okay. So
anyway, that's that debate. But we all agree to the הלכה halachah
*halakhah*. By the way, תוספות *Tosfos* has a whole discussion whether רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is really arguing on the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma*
or whether really רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is just clarifying and saying
even the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* did not really mean that there's
a מצות עשה mitzvot asei, *mitzvas asei* to get out of הר
הבית *Har HaBayis*. But anyway, פשט *pshat* is that they are debating
and there's a question whether a טבול יום *tvul yom* according to
this is allowed on הר הבית *Har HaBayis*, minimally it's an איסור
דרבנן d'rabbanan, *issur d'rabbanan*. Now, I want to pause for a moment
and just again, because I always love tying this into the one
relevant aspect about the הר הבית *Har HaBayis* tours, okay, so they
tell you, right, go to make sure like go to the מקוה
*mikvah* in the morning because they don't want to ask people like
did you have, you know, men, like did you have intercourse with
your wives, you know, do you have to—are you a טבול יום
*tvul yom*—are you a בעל קרי Baal Keri. *ba'al keri* or whatever
it is, so they just say go to the מקוה *mikvah* in
the morning. Okay, women, I hope they say if you're a נדה
*niddah* you can't come on the tour. Okay. But, let's assume that
the guy went to the מקוה *mikvah* in the morning, but he
actually had a seminal emission, he is a טבול יום *tvul yom*
of בעל קרי baal keri. *ba'al keri*. קרי. Okay, what is clear
from this is whether it's a מצות עשה or whether it's a
דרבנן, d'rabbanan. a טבול יום of בעל קרי baal keri. is not
allowed in עזרת נשים. Is not allowed on מחנה לויה. Maybe דאורייתא,
maybe a מצות עשה, maybe דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Okay, and again, it's just
my little pet peeve of mine that nobody says, you know, oh,
if you had a seminal emission, don't come on the tour today.
They say go to the מקוה in the morning and then you
can come on the tour, right? I don't know what they do
with the problem about a טבול יום. Okay, you know, it's not
a חיוב כרת, chiyuv kares. it's not an איסור לאו. issur lav.
At most it's a מצות עשה, but it's still an עשה or
דרבנן. d'rabbanan, So anyway, go figure that out. Okay? יהודה? רב יהודה?
Rav Yehudah? No, it's דרבנן, d'rabbanan it's rabbinic. Okay, חידשו בו דברים.
chidshu bo devarim. They innovated and they said, just because of פסח.
Pesach It's because of פסח Pesach. he's allowed. Everybody agrees we allow
for פסח. He's just saying it's not an עשה, it's a דרבנן
that we're allowing. Okay, so, ואמרת, v'amarta, now here was our problem.
Our problem is, fine, that's all fascinating, but why does this thing
work even if we allow the guy on הר הבית? Because the
מצורע's metzora got to stick his thumbs, he stands on this side
of the line because he's not allowed to enter the עזרה, Azarah.
and he's got to stick his thumbs into the עזרה Azarah? in
order to do the stuff with the blood. So that's ביאה במקצת.
bi'ah b'miktzat. Now, of course, the question could be wait, that's ביאה
במקצת bi'ah b'miktzat for the מצורע metzora as well, but the assumption
is okay, for the מצורע metzora you have no choice, that's obviously
has to be a special allowance. But if the guy's also a
בעל קרי, baal keri. even a טבול יום of a בעל קרי,
baal keri whatever you think about the status by הר הבית, everybody
agrees that you know until you're totally טהור you're not allowed in
the עזרה. Azarah So why is he allowed to stick his thumbs
into you know into the עזרה? Azarah, So that's what the גמרא
Gemara says. ואמרת ביאה במקצת שמה ביאה היכי מטי ידיה בבהונות? v'amarta
bi'ah b'miktzat sh'mah bi'ah heichi mati yadei b'vohonot? How does he stick
his hands for the sake of his thumbs? איידי דאתי עשה שיש
בו כרת הוא. aidi d'ati asei she'yesh bo kares hu. That's a
real כרת prohibition. Being in the עזרה when you are, you know,
when you are טמא. Even if you're only a טבול יום, טבול
יום of בעל קרי, baal keri. going in the עזרה, nobody debates
that's like a חיוב כרת. So how do we allow that to
happen if it really is an issue about ביאה במקצת? bi'ah b'miktzat?
אמר ליה amar lei he said back to him, מטונך, matuncha, which
is like מטונך matuncha literally means like your burden. So the way
sort of תוספות says, the burden you want to put on me,
I'm going to put back on you, like this is your problem,
this isn't my problem type of a statement. שאני מצורע הואיל והותר
לצרעתו הותר לקריו. shani metzora ho'il v'hutar l'tzara'ato hutar l'keryo. Look, who
allows this מצורע metzora stick his thumbs in? Okay, which is a
question you have to ask. That could be a challenge to ביאה
במקצת. bi'ah b'miktzat. How could you say ביאה במקצת bi'ah b'miktzat is
a problem? How does the מצורע metzora stick his thumbs in? So
the answer is that even if you say ביאה במקצת bi'ah b'miktzat
is a problem, you have to say implicitly the תורה Torah allows
that, waives that problem for a מצורע metzora, and allows him to
stick his thumbs in. Well, he's saying, once it waives the problem
for a מצורע, metzora and a מצורע metzora, is like the weightiest
טומאה, tumah it's going to waive the problem even you know for
him as a טבול יום. Okay? And we'll sort of say this
guy, we're going to ignore טומאה tumah issues when it comes to
sticking his thumbs in. So that was what it says, הואיל והותר
לקריו, ho'il v'hutar l'keryo, which presumably means okay, fine. So that's what
we're saying. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, so now we've got
the answer. How is this guy allowed to stick his thumbs in?
Because he got a special dispensation as a מצורע, metzora so that
dispensation applies for him even as a טבול יום of a בעל
קרי. baal keri אמר רב יוסף קסבר עולא רובן זבין. Amar Rav
Yosef kasavar Ulla ruban zavim. Now that we see this עולא Ulla
has presented this idea that if you get one dispensation it applies
to a lighter טומאה tumah status, we can infer the following הלכה.
Halakha Okay, עולא Ulla must be of the opinion that רובן זבין
ונעשו טמאי מתים. ruban zavim v'na'asu t'mei meitim. The הלכה is if
that רוב rov of the ציבור's tzibur טמא, you bring a קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach. בטומאה. b'tumah. But that's only by טומאת מת, tumat
meis, a טומאה tumah contracted from the outside. If רוב rov of
the ציבור tzibur is טמא because, you know, they're זבין zavim or
בעלי קרי baalei keri or whatever it might be, well, whatever, let's
say זבין, zavim, then you don't get to bring a קרבן פסח.
Korban Pesach You don't say טומאה הותרה בציבור. tumah hutrah b'tzibur. Let's
say they're both. They're רוב, rov, the majority of the ציבור tzibur
is both זב zav and טמאי מתים. t'mei meitim. Okay, do you
say טומאה הותרה בציבור? tumah hutrah b'tzibur? So he's saying well, based
on עולא, Ulla, if you get a dispensation for one, it applies
to the other, so presumably you do get to bring a קרבן
פסח. Korban Pesach. Okay, so let's take a look. קסבר עולא רובן
זבין, kasavar Ulla ruban zavim, if most of the ציבור tzibur were
זבין, zavim, men, ונעשו טמאי מתים, v'na'asu t'mei meitim, and then they
became טמאי מתים, t'mei meitim, הואיל והותרו לטומאתן, ho'il v'hutru l'tumatan, since
they get a dispensation to bring the קרבן פסח korban pesach because
it's טומאה הותרה בציבור tumah hutrah b'tzibur for טמאי מתים, t'mei meitim,
הותרו לזיבתן, hutru l'zivatan, they also get a dispensation for their זיבה
zivah status. אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said one
minute, you got the order reversed. Yeah, exactly. מי דמי? mi dami?
Who can compare it? טומאה אשתראי זיבה לא אשתראי. tumah ishtara'i zivah
lo ishtara'i. The זב zav. status came first. So the new טומאה
tumah status that they, that they sort of you know acquired does
not you know that won't forbid them in the קרבן פסח. korban
pesach. Okay, but that doesn't, that doesn't affect their טומאה tumah status,
they were already excluded as זבין. zavim. So just because they're now
טומאת מת tumas meis status doesn't exclude them, and it doesn't help
with their pre-existing זב zav status. He says the order has to
be the same as the order here. First מצורע metzora and then
בעל קרי. ba'al keri Well, right, exactly. The order has to be
the same like we had it here. First מצורע metzora and then
בעל קרי. ba'al keri, You start with your dispensation and then you
remain with a permission to go ahead and the same way the
מצורע metzora started with a permission to stick in his thumbs, that
permission continues when he gets a sort of an additional lesser status.
But you have to start with the permission, okay? That's his basic
assumption. So he says, אמר ליה דילמא הכי קאמרת, amar lei dilma
hachi kamart, maybe this is what you meant to say, the reverse
order. ראובן Reuven טמאי מתים, tmei meisim, if the majority of the
ציבור tzibur is טמאי מתים, tmei meisim, so they already then started
with a dispensation to bring a קרבן פסח korban pesach. even though
they're טמא. ונעשו זבים, venasu zavim, and then they became a זב,
zav הואיל והותרה לטומאתן הותרה לזיבתן, ho'il vehutra letumasam hutra lezivasam, since
the dispensation already applied for their טמא מת tmei meis status, it
continues to apply for, they remain with a permission to bring a
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach Now even there you could אמר ליה, amar
lei, so he said back to him, אין, yes you're right, that's
what I want to say. Yes, he says that's what I want
to say. Okay? But of course even there you could make a
difference because even though they started with a dispensation, a זב zav.
status is weightier in certain ways than a טמא מת tmei meis
status, whereas here a dispensation for מצורע metzora. works for dispensation for
בעל קרי. ba'al keri. בעל קרי ba'al keri. is much lighter than
מצורע. metzora So it's logical that if you have a dispensation for
your מצורע metzora status it'll apply to your lighter status. So that
doesn't get challenged, okay? But the גמרא's Gemara going to, I don't
know, the גמרא's Gemara going to challenge it from another perspective. But
if you say the dispensation that you start with continues for other
things, logically that should be true by a טמא מת tmei meis
who becomes a זב. zav, If you start with a dispensation it
should continue, ignoring the fact that a זב zav is an even
weightier type of a טומאה tumah status. But the גמרא Gemara is
not satisfied even then. So the גמרא Gemara, says like this: והא
לא דמי, ve'ati lo dami, one minute says the גמרא, Gemara even
that's not similar. מצורע היתרא הוא הואיל והוי אישתרי אישתרי. metzora hutra
hu hovei ishtarei ishtarei. מצורע metzora, is fundamentally the תורה Torah by
telling you here's how you do the טהרה tahara of מצורע, metzora
the תורה is basically telling you like it's מצורע's, metzora the thumbs
are הותרה. hutra. It's like we are completely ignoring the fact that
there's any problem at all. טומאה דחויה הוא. tumah dchuya hu. טומאה
tumah, however, this is the classic הותרה hutra versus דחויה. dchuya. טומאה
tumah basically means there's a problem, but we're overriding it, as opposed
to הותרה hutra which means in this case there's no problem at
all. Okay? It's sort of like when you're מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos
to save a life. Do you say I'm מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos
but I was allowed to be מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos because the
saving of a life is more important than חילול שבת? chillul Shabbos?
That's a דחויה dchuya type of a framing. א הותרה a hutra
type of a framing is the תורה never prohibited שבת Shabbos acts
in the context of saving a life. I wasn't מחלל שבת mechallel
Shabbos at all, right? It wasn't that there was no prohibition, the
prohibition doesn't apply here. Okay, so here too. The גמרא's Gemara, assuming
by a מצורע metzora since it's part of the טהרה tahara process
of a מצורע metzora that it's not like that the טומאה tumah
is overridden to allow you to stick in your thumbs, it's like
there's no fundamental problem in this person by sticking the thumbs in.
Okay, and if that's true, if it's a complete הותרה, hutra, it'll
apply to him even if he's also a בעל קרי. ba'al keri
So there we can understand it. Whereas טומאה, tuma it's like there
is a problem here, but we're going to override the טומאה tuma.
to allow you to bring a קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach טומאה דחויה
היא להא אדחי להא לא אדחי. tumah dchuya hi leha idchi leha
lo idchi. Because we recognize a problem, we're going to still be
contending with the complications of the issue and we're going to say
fine, we can override the טומאת מת, tumas meis, it's not going
to allow us to override the זב issue. Okay, so regardless of
which came first, in this case, the power of the override is
weaker and therefore it can't work for more problems. It can only
work for the problems it can work for. By the way, this
could be very dangerous by שבת Shabbos because by שבת Shabbos if
somebody has the mentality I'm מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos but it's allowed,
a דחויה dchuya mentality, somebody would say wait a minute, but maybe
I should do it this way which minimizes my חילול שבת chillul
Shabbos rather than doing it that way which means I'm doing more
מלאכות, melachos, and you know the גמרא, Gemara it's very clear in
הלכה you're not supposed to be making those חשבונות. cheshbonos. Obviously that
could come at the risk of somebody's life. Okay, but that's the
type of mentality, oh you're constantly contending with problems so you have
to try to minimize them. So the גמרא says if טומאה tuma
is דחויה dchuya and we have to minimize, so maybe it only
works for the טומאת מת, tumas meis, it doesn't work for the
זב. That's one response. אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, so רבא
Rava says, and I got to tell you, I really agree here
with רבא, Rava, אדרבה איפכא מסתברא. adderaba ipcha mistabra. No, it's the
exact opposite logic. מצורע היתרא הוא להא אישתרי להא לא אישתרי. metzora
hutra hu leha ishtarei leha lo ishtarei. By מצורע metzora we never
articulated an
idea, oh to make you טהור that's going to override problems. If
you're saying it's הותרה hutra what we're saying is there is no
problem. Fine, there's no problem for you as a מצורע metzora to
stick your thumbs in. That doesn't mean that if you're a בעל
קרי ba'al keri, who ever allowed you
to stick your thumbs in, right? We never articulated an idea that
there's a certain value here that's important enough to override. That's what
you frame when you say דחויה. dchuya. When you say הותרה... hutra...
You're not even acknowledging that a problem existed and that one thing
is more important than the other. You're just saying it doesn't exist.
Okay? So fine. So thumbs of a מצורע metzora. is a non-problem.
But thumbs of a בעל קרי is a problem, even in the
process of being מטהר mitaher a מצורע. metzora, So if it's הותרה,
hutra, that's not relevant to the thumbs of a בעל קרי, even
if it's the same guy. Okay? טומאה דחויה היא. tuma dchuya hi.
But if טומאה tuma is being pushed away, we're making a statement:
it's more important that you bring a קרבן פסח even if it
requires us overriding a problem of טומאה. So you're saying there's an
override. You're saying קרבן פסח is weightier. Okay? If that's what you're
saying, so once it's going to override for one, even though it
normally doesn't override זב, it only overrides טמי מת, tmei meit, but
maybe in some cases if it's already overriding טמי מת, tmei meit,
it should override other things as well. מה לי חדא דחויה מה
לי שתי דחיות? ma li chada dchuya ma li shtei dchuyos? What
do I care, one or two? Now again, I do care because
it doesn't override זב by itself. But once it gets the power
of overriding, it should be able to override more things. I gotta
tell you, to me Rava's argument makes more sense. It's not just
stronger versus weaker, it's what's the mechanism. Not recognizing a problem doesn't
allow you to deal with other problems like I guess is a
good מוסר שמועס mussar shmooze here. Okay? If you don't recognize the
problem, right, so you recognize and you say, even so, here's how
we're going to deal with it, that can be relevant to other
problems as well. Okay? And now we'll just read the first point.
So if this guy's a whatever it is, like the eighth day
מצורע, metzora whatever you want to call him, and he's also a
בעל קרי. Right? So Rava is saying that according to this logic,
if ביאה במקצת שמי ביאה, bi'ah b'mikzat shmei bi'ah, then you can't
explain why the guy can stick his, you know, can stick his
thumbs in if he's a בעל קרי. So then Rava would say
you couldn't? You would have to say ביאה במקצת לא שמי ביאה.
bi'ah b'mikzat lo shmei bi'ah. That's correct. What is, what would Rava,
is Rava saying? Yes, that's implicitly, yes. Okay, so Michael's correct to
tie it back. So bottom line, we have a question: how could
this מצורע metzora on the day eight stick his thumbs in even
if he's allowed to go into עזרת נשים? How's he allowed to
stick his thumbs in? Right? And the answer is if ביאה במקצת
שמי ביאה, bi'ah b'mikzat shmei bi'ah, so either the answer is the
override for מצורע metzora applied to the override for בעל קרי and
allowed him to stick his thumbs in, or according to Rava, no,
it doesn't work. That's a הותרה, hutra, not a דחויה, dchuya, etcetera,
and the only reason he's allowed to stick his thumbs in is
because ביאה במקצת לא שמי ביאה. bi'ah b'mikzat lo shmei bi'ah. It's
one or the other. Okay? And that's going to turn us to
now, we're sort of transition from ביאה במקצת bi'ah b'mikzat to the
next discussion. So I'll just read the first line. So now for
tomorrow, the next discussion is going to be: מכלל דתרוייהו סבירא להו
טומאה דחויה בציבור. michlal d'travaihu svira lehu tuma dchuya b'tzibur. Ah, so
both of them, they're arguing which is better, דחויה dchuya or הותרה
hutra in our context. But they both agree that טומאה is דחויה
בציבור. dchuya b'tzibur. That מצורע metzora, is הותרה, hutra, right, for the
thumbs, and טומאה is דחויה. dchuya. That was they both agree, and
they were just arguing which one more logically would permit this case
rather than that case. Okay, so tomorrow we're going to transition to,
today the discussion was ביאה במקצת, bi'ah b'mikzat, where we had a
debate, two ways of understanding the מצורע, metzora either ביאה במקצת bi'ah
b'mikzat is not a problem with the thumbs, or that it's a
special היתר heter that would apply to the מצורע metzora. and also
to the בעל קרי, or fundamentally it's, or basically ביאה במקצת bi'ah
b'mikzat it wasn't a problem to begin with or it was a
special allowance for a מצורע. And now we're going to tomorrow discuss
the issue about טומאה דחויה tuma dchuya or הותרה בציבור. hutra b'tzibur.
Okay? So to be continued tomorrow.